All right, the next section in the text, ovarian tumors.
Before we can begin this discussion,
we've got to understand a little bit of normal,
so let's go to the whiteboard.
Remind ourselves that this is the ovary,
that the ovary histologically contains three major compartments.
It contains the oocyte, or the egg,
and from this oocyte, or egg, we can derive germ cell tumors.
It contains the cells that support the oocyte,
for example, the granulosa cells, the theca cells,
and the fibroblasts, which are the stromal cells
that are the connective tissue of the ovary,
and that entire category is called the sex cord stroma,
and so from that, we can derive sex cord stromal tumors,
and then the third possibility is that the ovary
is lined by surface epithelium.
The entire surface of the ovary has surface epithelium,
and from this surface epithelium, we can derive tumors,
and those are called surface epithelial tumors.
So once you understand this normal,
then you understand that there are three major categories
of ovarian tumors.
Now there's a fourth possibility, which would be metastasis.
However, metastasis is going to be put off
until the very end of this discussion,
and we'll just discuss for now
the three categories of primary tumors of the ovary.
Now what I say here in your text
is that the ovary has three cell types.
Of course, it's surface epithelium, germ cells,
and sex cord stroma,
and tumor can arise from any of these cell types
or from metastasis, which again we'll discuss
at the very end of this section.
We'll start with the surface epithelial tumors
because they are the most common type of ovarian tumor,
and what I'd like to remind you
is that the surface epithelium of the ovary,
the surface lining of the ovary,
is also known as celomic epithelium.
Now this epithelium has the ability
to produce multiple different cell types,
just as the gyne tract
has multiple different cell types.
For example, you're well aware
that the fallopian tube is normally lined by serous cells,
and that the endometrium is normally lined
by endometrial type cells,
and that the endocervix is lined by mucinous type cells.
And so this celomic epithelium that lines the ovary
also has the ability to produce
multiple different cell types.
And there's four different cell types
that we're gonna talk about,
but we're gonna start with the two most common.
The two most common cell types
that can arise with surface epithelial tumors
are serous tumors and mucinous tumors.
Now the way you wanna think about these
is that serous tumors and mucinous tumors
are usually cystic,
so that would be principle number one,
and that they are classically named
based on the type of fluid that they would produce.
So you'd have this big cystic tumor,
and if it was full of water when you cut it open,
we would call that a serous tumor.
And if it was full of mucus when you cut it open,
we would call that a mucinous tumor.
And this is the way that we classically named these tumors.
Now we can look under the microscope
and we can confirm whether the cells
are really serous or mucinous,
but that's a very sort of introductory way
to look at these tumors.
So the two most common tumors of the surface
are serous tumors and mucinous tumors.
Both are usually cystic.
When you have a serous tumor, it's usually full of water.
When you have a mucinous tumor,
it's usually full of mucus.
Now in addition, when you have surface epithelial tumors,
you can categorize those tumors based on how they behave.
So there are benign tumors, there are malignant tumors,
and then there are tumors in between,
which are called borderline tumors.
Now the benign tumors are called cyst adenoma.
In particular, when we're dealing with the serous
and the mucinous types,
they're going to be called cyst adenoma.
And that's because I told you that the serous tumors
make watery fluid producing a cyst,
and the mucinous tumors make mucousy fluid producing a cyst.
So if it's benign, it'll be called cyst because it's cystic,
and adeno because it's glandular cells,
and then oma because it's a benign mass.
So cyst adenoma.
Now the way by which we recognize a cyst adenoma
is that when you look at it on gross examination,
it is a single simple cyst,
and were you to look under the microscope,
you would see a simple flat lining to that cyst.
And so that's the classic feature of a cyst adenoma.
Now most commonly, these tumors arise in premenopausal women,
classically around the age of 30 to 40.
And that's going to be important as we move forward.
So here's what a cyst adenoma looks like.
This is the cyst opened up,
and this is sort of half of it and the other half of it.
And you can imagine, let's pretend,
if that was full of watery fluid
and the cells looked serous under the microscope,
we would call that a serous cyst adenoma.
If it was full of mucousy fluid
and the cells looked mucinous under the microscope,
we would call that a mucinous cyst adenoma.
Again, both are benign.
Both would be seen around the age of 30 to 40 years of age.
The only other thing that I would like to say here
is that the way by which we can prove that they're benign
is when we look under the microscope,
we would see that the entire cyst was lined
by just a simple single layer of epithelial cells.
Now, in the malignant variant, we call that cyst adenocarcinoma.
Cyst because it's cystic,
adeno because the cells are glandular,
and then carcinoma because it's a malignant epithelial tumor,
so cyst adenocarcinoma.
Now, again, when you have a cyst adenocarcinoma,
you're going to have a large tumor,
and when you cut it open,
rather than having a simple single cyst,
you're going to have very complicated cysts, multiple cysts,
and then when you look at the lining,
instead of having that nice, smooth, shiny lining,
you'll actually see a shaggy lining, almost like a carpet,
and so that's the classic features of the malignant tumor.
Now, again, if it's a big cystic lesion
and you cut into it and water comes out,
you think about cirrus cyst adenocarcinoma,
and if it's a big tumor, cystic tumor,
and you cut it open and mucinous fluid comes out
or mucous fluid comes out,
then you think about a mucinous cyst adenocarcinoma.
You can confirm that by looking at the histology
to see whether the cells look cirrus
or whether they look mucinous,
but the key feature here, again,
is complex cysts with thick, shaggy lining.
Now, of course, the defining feature of this malignancy
would be that the cells invade
into the connective tissue of the cyst wall,
so you'd have clear invasion of cells
into the connective tissue,
which would then define that tumor
to be absolutely malignant.
Now, this commonly arises in postmenopausal women.
For example, the average age would be about 65 years of age.
There is a third category for surface epithelial tumors,
and those are called borderline tumors.
The only thing you have to know about borderline tumors
is that they have features in between benign and malignant.
They are malignant.
They have metastatic potential.
However, they behave much better
than the clear-cut malignant tumors,
and so because they're sort of in between,
we call them borderline tumors.
Again, it's important to note that they have a better prognosis,
but they still carry metastatic potential
in that they are still malignant.
Now, one important association here
that's high yield for examinations,
especially board examinations,
is the fact that BRCA mutation carriers
can get a specific type of ovarian carcinoma.
Let's go back and remind ourselves
that patients who have BRCA1 mutations,
they have an increased risk of breast cancer,
but in addition to that,
they also have an increased risk of ovarian cancer.
It's not enough to know just that.
You need to go one step further
and know that the most classic type of tumor
that arises in the ovary in these patients
is a serous carcinoma.
So these patients would get a surface epithelial tumor
that was malignant,
and it would be of the serous subtype.
So that's important to know
concerning BRCA1 mutation carriers.
The second important thing to know about these patients
is that not only do they have an increased risk of ovary,
but they also have an increased risk of serous carcinoma
of the fallopian tube.
And of course, that has clinical implications
because when patients have a BRCA mutation,
they may elect to, for example, remove both breasts
to reduce the risk of breast cancer.
And they may also elect to remove the ovary
and the fallopian tube,
and they would have to remove the fallopian tube
to remove the risk of fallopian tube serous carcinoma as well.
And so that is an important clinical principle,
and so therefore it becomes high yield for examinations.
Now, I've only told you about two
of the surface epithelial tumors,
which is that you can have serous tumors
or you can have mucinous tumors.
There are two other types
that are relatively high yield for exam.
The first is endometrioid surface tumors.
So we can have a surface epithelial tumor
that has endometrioid histology.
What do we mean by endometrioid?
We mean that it looks like endometrial cells.
So that's one possibility.
Now, a few things to know about endometrioid tumors
of the surface of the ovary.
The first point is that they're usually malignant.
Remember that surface epithelial tumors
can be benign, borderline, or malignant.
When you have an endometrioid tumor,
it's usually malignant.
So you're going to have an endometrioid carcinoma.
That's point one.
Point number two is that it usually arises,
or I shouldn't say usually,
but it may be associated with endometriosis.
This goes back to the discussion that we had
when we talked about endometriosis.
If you review your notes there,
you'll see that I said that in endometriosis,
one of the complications was that carcinoma
could develop particularly in the ovary.
And so there's an association of endometrioid carcinoma
with endometriosis.
And then the other important association
is that when patients have endometrioid carcinoma,
15% of those patients will actually have
a separate endometrioid carcinoma
in the endometrium as well.
So 15% of patients with endometrioid carcinoma
of the ovary will also have
a separate endometrioid carcinoma
in the endometrium.
And so when we have patients
with endometrioid carcinoma of the ovary,
it's important to know, especially for exams,
that we also need to look
and see what's going on in their endometrium.
There may be a cancer there as well.
The fourth type of surface epithelial tumor
is called a Brenner tumor.
The only thing for examination purposes
is that the Brenner tumor usually contains urothelium
as its type of epithelium.
So if you've got an ovarian tumor
and they tell you that the ovarian tumor
contains cells that mimic the,
or that resemble urothelium,
then we would call that a Brenner tumor.
And that is a high yield principle
to be aware of as well.
Now, generally speaking,
when we talk about the surface epithelial tumors,
it's important to know that they present late.
And that's going to result in a poor prognosis.
Remember, the general principle in neoplasia
is that the longer the tumor can grow in the patient,
the more it can pick up mutations.
The more it picks up mutations,
the more it's going to be,
the more malignant it's going to become over time.
The surface epithelial tumors,
there's a lot of room in the pelvis
for the ovary to grow,
and so these tumors present late.
Now, they present with also very vague symptoms.
For example, abdominal pain or fullness,
signs of compression with urinary frequency, et cetera.
One of the mechanisms by which
ovarian epithelial tumors spread
is locally,
and they like to extend to involve the peritoneum.
Remember that we talked about three mechanisms of spread
in our neoplasia lecture,
and we said that carcinomas like to go to lymphatics.
The sarcomas like to go hematogenously and then spread,
and then we mentioned at that point
that the ovary liked to spread locally
and involve the peritoneum.
And in particular,
I showed you a picture there
of a patient who had massive involvement of the omentum,
and I told you that were you to cut through that,
you would see something called omental caking.
And so when you cut through it,
it kind of looks like cake.
So they call that omental caking,
and that's a high-yield thing to be aware of,
as I've already mentioned previously.
The surface epithelial tumors,
one of the interesting things
that they may release into the serum is CA-125.
CA-125 is a serum tumor marker.
Remember that serum tumor markers,
generally speaking,
can provide three separate benefits.
They can be used for screening.
They can be used to monitor treatment,
response,
and they can also be used to monitor recurrence.
In the case of screening,
CA-125 is not really panned out to be useful.
However, in the case of monitoring treatment
and recurrence, it has.
So for example,
if a patient has a surface epithelial tumor
and the CA-125 is high,
once it's removed surgically,
the CA-125 should again go down
and should decrease to zero.
So that's one important way
by which we could use the CA-125.
And another important way
by which we could use the CA-125
is to screen for recurrence.
So let's say that a woman comes in,
she's got a history of serous carcinoma of the ovary,
and at the time of diagnosis,
her CA-125 was high.
Now she comes in,
I don't know,
a year later after surgical removal,
and she's having symptoms
that suggest that there's recurrence of the tumor,
and a CA-125 is measured,
and it's high again.
And that would be a pretty good indication
that the patient now has recurrence.
So that would be something to consider
concerning CA-125.
The second category of tumors
that can arise in the ovary
are called the germ cell tumors.
This is the second most common ovarian tumor.
It's seen in 15% of the cases.
So of all of the ovarian tumors,
15% of cases are germ cell tumors.
Usually occurs in women of reproductive age.
This is important because it allows us
to make a distinction clinically
and on examinations
of what we're actually considering
when we deal with a particular patient.
So for example,
if you're dealing with a woman
who's about the age of 15 to 30,
then I would think about a germ cell tumor.
So that would be high on my differential.
If I'm dealing with a woman that's 35 or 40,
I'm thinking of a benign surface epithelial tumor.
And if I'm dealing with a woman
that's, for example, 60 or 70,
my differential diagnosis at the top
is a malignant surface epithelial tumor.
So again, the age becomes important
when you look at a clinical vignette, for example.
Now the germ cell tumors,
a lot of students are sort of terrified
of these tumors
because it's hard to remember the types
and exactly what's going on.
But I actually think it's relatively easy
if you just remember
what the normal germ cell can make.
And based on what it can make,
you can then subsequently
sort of put the pieces together
and know the different tumors that can form.
For example, I'll show you how I do this.
So when I think about the germ cell,
I remind myself that the germ cell
can make fetal tissues, correct?
It's going to be able to make baby.
And so when it's going to make fetal-type tissues,
one tumor that would resemble fetal tissues
would be something called a cystic teratoma.
So a cystic teratoma is, again,
a tumor that contains different embryologic layers.
For example, it contains skin and teeth
and bone and hair and gut
and thyroid tissue, et cetera.
And so that's one example.
So we call that a cystic teratoma.
All right.
You can also get fetal-type tissue
that's very primitive in a germ cell tumor.
And we call that embryonal carcinoma.
Embryonal, i.e. embryo-like,
so that when you look at the cells
under the microscope,
they look very primitive,
almost like the embryo-like cells.
So that's embryonal carcinoma.
Another important type of tissue
that the germ cell is going to make,
it's going to make the yolk sac.
And so from that type of tissue,
we can have something called a yolk sac tumor.
Another type of tissue that the germ cell can make,
it can make additional germ cells.
And when you have a tumor of a mass
of a bunch of germ cells,
we call that dysgerminoma.
All right, dysgerminoma.
And then in addition,
the oocyte or the egg
needs to be able to make placenta.
And so we can have a tumor of placental tissue,
and that's called choriocarcinoma.
And all of this basically summarizes
the different types of germ cell tumors.
So there are five key germ cell tumors
to be aware of,
and all of them are explained here.
And now I'm going to walk you through them one by one.
So the first of these germ cell tumors
is a cystic teratoma.
Again, what is a cystic teratoma?
It's a cystic tumor, hence the term cystic,
that's comprised of fetal tissue,
and that is derived from two or three embryonic layers
or embryologic layers.
It's the most common germ cell tumor in females,
and 10% of the time, these tumors can be bilateral.
So it would not be uncommon,
even on an examination,
to have a tumor on both the right side
and the left side in a particular patient.
This is what the cystic teratoma looks like.
Basically, it's a tumor, again,
composed of hair, teeth, bone, gut, thyroid,
basically any normal tissue
that could be seen in a fetus.
It's a cystic tumor.
This cyst here has been opened,
and we can see that this is full of hair.
Now, there's probably a tooth over here
or maybe a piece of bone,
and then there's all of this debris
that's coming off of the skin
because these tumors often have
a tremendous amount of skin.
Now, cystic teratomas are benign,
and that's a good thing
because it's the most common germ cell tumor
in a female.
However, whenever we have a cystic teratoma,
we need to exclude two things
to ensure that the tumor is actually benign.
The first thing that we need to exclude
is the presence of immature tissue.
If there's immature tissue in the teratoma,
it then becomes an immature teratoma
instead of a mature teratoma,
and then it would potentially have malignant potential.
It has the ability to spread outside of the region.
So that would be something to worry about.
One question that likes to show up on examinations
is what's the most common type of tissue
that's immature in an immature teratoma,
and the answer is neural ectoderm.
So often, immature teratomas contain neural ectoderm,
which then indicates that they're an immature teratoma.
Another possibility that could occur within a teratoma
is that the tissue of the teratoma
actually has a cancer.
Now, you know that a teratoma contains all mature tissue,
like mature skin, mature gut, mature bone, et cetera.
It is possible that the tissue in the teratoma
can actually have a cancer.
For example, in the skin of the teratoma,
you can have a squamous cell carcinoma,
and that's called a somatic malignancy.
And, of course, that would also have malignant potential
and could potentially spread in the patient,
and so that would also raise a concern for us,
and we would no longer call this a benign teratoma,
but instead we would say
it's a teratoma with somatic malignancy.
Now, another important question
that shows up on examinations,
what's the most common somatic malignancy
that arises in a teratoma,
and the answer is squamous cell carcinoma
of the skin of the teratoma.
One special type of teratoma is called struma ovariae.
In this particular case,
you have a teratoma that's mostly composed of thyroid tissue,
and so sometimes patients can develop hyperthyroidism
because the teratoma contains thyroid tissue,
and the thyroid tissue is hyperfunctioning.
So let's say that you've got a woman,
she's about the age of 20,
and they tell you that she's also got hyperthyroidism
along with a mass in the ovary.
One of the things to consider would be a teratoma
that's mostly made up of thyroid tissue.
Again, we call that struma ovariae.
So that's the first type of germ cell tumor.
That is cystic teratoma,
and, of course, that's the most common germ cell tumor.
The next germ cell tumor is called dysgerminoma.
Dysgerminoma means bad.
German refers to the, in this particular case,
the germ cells, and oma refers to a mass.
So it is a mass of a bunch of egg-like cells or germ cells,
and that's why we say here that histologically
it's composed of large cells
with clear cytoplasm and central nuclei.
That resembles the oocyte,
and this description is that of the oocyte, basically.
Now this is the most common malignant germ cell tumor.
Remember that the most common benign germ cell tumor
and the most common germ cell tumor overall
is a cystic teratoma.
So this is the most common malignant germ cell tumor.
When we have this tumor in the testicle,
it's called a seminoma,
and when we do testicular tumors,
we'll talk about seminoma in more detail.
This tumor has good prognosis,
or it responds well to radiotherapy,
and one of the tumor markers that can be increased
with a dysgerminoma is LDH.
So that may be seen in the serum.
This is what the tumor looks like.
You have these nests of cells,
but the nests are all sort of composed of these round cells,
and so this is the classic feature of a dysgerminoma.
The next tumor is called endodermal sinus tumor.
The idea here is that you have a tumor
that mimics the yolk sac.
What's important, there's three high yields
to be familiar with with the endodermal sinus tumor.
Number one, it's the most common germ cell tumor in kids.
So if you've got a five-year-old girl with an ovarian mass,
you really want to think about the endodermal sinus tumor.
Number two, just as the yolk sac,
it produces alpha-fetoprotein,
so that when you have a high alpha-fetoprotein,
you want to think about an endodermal sinus tumor,
especially in a child with an ovarian mass, for example.
And then finally, on histology,
we see something called Schiller-Duval bodies.
Now Schiller-Duval bodies are what is classically described
as glomeruloid-like structures.
So they're almost glomerular-like
from the glomerulus of the kidney.
And this is what it looks like.
You've got a blood vessel in the center,
and then you've sort of got these cells
all around that blood vessel
that are organizing around it,
and then you've got another layer of cells outside of that.
Sort of like this would be Bowman's capsule,
and then this would be Bowman's space.
And so one of the descriptions of this
and the one they like to show on examinations
or give you on examinations is to say that
biopsies performed and glomeruloid-like structures are seen.
And so you're not going to think about
some kind of kidney tumor.
You're going to think about an endodermal sinus tumor.
And again, these are also known as Schiller-Duval bodies.
The next of the germ cell tumors is called choriocarcinoma.
What's choriocarcinoma?
It is a malignant proliferation of placental-like tissue.
Now, basically, what you should remind yourselves
of placental tissue is that normally
when you have placental tissue, you have villi.
This is the functional unit of the placenta.
You've got a villus.
Of course, there's a blood vessel
that runs through the villus.
And remember that the cells that surround the villus
are called cytotrophoblasts.
And another cell that surrounds the villus
is called a syncytiotrophoblasts,
where you've got multiple nuclei in a cell, for example.
So trophoblasts, whether they be syncytiotrophoblasts,
or cytotrophoblasts, trophoblasts is the key cell
that surrounds the villus.
Now, in a choriocarcinoma, what happens is that you get
a malignant proliferation of these trophoblasts.
There will be no villi.
That's important.
There are no villi.
Instead, you have a malignant proliferation
of just the trophoblasts.
And that's what I've stated here in your book.
It's a tumor composed of trophoblasts,
both syncytiotrophoblasts and cytotrophoblasts,
and the villi are absent, so there should be no villi.
Now, classically, this is a small hemorrhagic tumor
that spreads very quickly throughout the body.
The reason that this can spread early through the body,
despite the fact that it's only a small tumor in the ovary,
is because this tumor is genetically programmed
to invade blood vessels from the very beginning,
from its very inception.
And that's because you're well aware of the fact
that trophoblasts are designed to invade and find blood vessels.
That's sort of their natural genetic program.
And so when you get a tumor of these cells,
they very quickly go into the blood,
they spread through the blood,
and then they spread all over the body.
So this is one of the rare tumors in pathology
where you have a tiny primary in the ovary,
but you've got massive tumor all over the body.
And again, that's because these cells
are genetically programmed to go into the blood.
So that's one important gross description.
Choriocarcinoma will do what trophoblasts normally do.
In particular, remember that the syncytial trophoblasts,
they can produce beta-HCG,
and so these tumors will have a high beta-HCG.
Very important to know that patients with choriocarcinoma
have a poor response to chemotherapy.
So choriocarcinoma, when it's a germ cell tumor,
has a poor response to chemotherapy.
And I'm going to touch on this in a little more detail
when we cover the gestational lecture
and talk about the different types
of hydotetiform moles.
But I want to just bury away this principle
in the back of your mind.
It's going to come up one more time
at the very end of this chapter.
So I'm going to remind you one more time
that choriocarcinoma, when it's a germ cell tumor,
the germ cell variant of choriocarcinoma,
has a poor response to chemotherapy.
The last of the germ cell tumors
is called embrinal carcinoma.
Now, the idea here is that you have a tumor
with cells that look very primitive,
almost embryo-like,
and that's called embrinal carcinoma.
This tumor is aggressive with early metastasis,
and that kind of makes sense
because the embryo-like cells would,
when they're primitive,
they have the ability to move and spread.
That's what primitive cells do,
and so that's exactly what these cells do,
and that's called, again, embrinal carcinoma.
The third category of ovarian tumors
are the sex cord stromal tumors,
and these are tumors that resemble
the normal sex cord stromal tissue of the ovary,
and remember that we talked about this previously
and said that we've got,
among the sex cord stromal tissues,
we've got granulosa cells and theca cells,
whose role is to support the oocyte.
We've got fibrous tissue,
and then very rarely,
we can also have tumors
that are going to arise from Sertoli cells
and Leydig cells,
and we're going to talk about that
in more detail in a moment.
So the first example
would be the granulosa theca cell tumor.
This is a tumor of both granulosa and theca cells.
It often produces estrogen,
and remember that the theca cells produce androgen,
which then gets converted
by the granulosa cells to estrogen.
That's the normal physiology,
and so in this tumor as well,
the granulosa cells are going to produce estrogen,
and that's going to be
the dominant hormone present in the blood.
So patients are going to present
with signs and symptoms of estrogen excess.
Now, granulosa theca cell tumors
can actually develop in infants or children,
young children.
They can develop in middle-aged women,
and they can develop in older adults.
If you get a granulosa theca cell tumor
in a young child before puberty,
then the child would present
with signs and symptoms of precocious puberty
or early puberty.
If you got a granulosa theca cell tumor
in a middle-aged adult,
then the woman would present
with heavy menstrual bleeding
or maybe bleeding outside
of the menstrual cycle, for example.
And then if you got this tumor
in an older adult that was postmenopausal,
then they would have abnormal uterine bleeding
or postmenopausal bleeding,
and that's because the estrogen from the tumor
is going to hit the endometrium
and cause the endometrium to grow
and grow and grow,
and eventually it would begin to bleed.
So that's the granulosa theca cell tumor.
Sertoli lidic cell tumor is a tumor
that mimics the sex cord stromal elements
of the testicle.
Remember that when you think about
the sex cord stromal elements of the testicle,
the testicle contains these tubules,
and remember that it's within these tubules
that you have the sperm forming.
And then outside of the tubules
you have these pink cells
that are present on occasion.
Those are called lidic cells,
and these are the sex cord stromal cells
of the testicle.
Now because the ovary and testicle
have similar embryologic origins,
it is possible to get a Sertoli lidic cell tumor
in the ovary.
So the Sertoli cells would form tubules
as I've just described.
The lidic cells,
what's important about them
is that they contain a characteristic crystal,
which is called a Rehnke crystal.
And you do need to be aware of Rehnke crystals
for examinations.
If you've got a tumor
and there's these pink cells
that contain crystals,
then you want to think about
a lidic cell component.
And of course these tumors
are going to produce androgen,
and so women can get hertstuism,
which is hair in a male distribution,
for example,
they may develop facial hair,
or virilization.
That's another possibility
if you've got excess androgen.
The third type of sex cord stromal tumor
is a fibroma.
This is very high yield
for the purposes of board exams.
It's a benign tumor of fibroblasts.
But what's even more important than that
is that it's associated
with pleural effusion and ascites
in a subset of patients.
And that is called Meigs syndrome.
So a woman who's got an ovarian tumor
with pleural effusion and ascites,
that entire complex is called Meigs syndrome.
Now this is what an ovarian fibroma looks like.
Basically it's a solid tumor
with all these white bands running through it,
and these white bands represent the fibrosis,
i.e. because we're dealing with a fibroma.
The last of the tumors to involve the ovary
would be metastatic tumor
that comes from another site
and then spreads to the ovary.
There are many cancers
that can spread to the ovary.
We're only going to discuss two classic examples.
The first is called the Krukenberg tumor,
and the idea here is that we get
a mucinous carcinoma
from some site outside of the ovary
that then subsequently metastasizes
and spreads to both ovaries
so that both ovaries are then involved
by mucinous carcinoma.
Now the site, the primary site
of this particular tumor
can arise from a couple places.
Classically, the most common primary site
would be to have a gastric carcinoma,
in particular the diffuse subtype
of gastric carcinoma.
Now let's remind ourselves
that when we think about gastric carcinoma,
there's actually two subtypes.
There's an intestinal type
and there is a diffuse type.
Remember that in the diffuse type,
the characteristic cell that we would see
would be something called the signet ring cell.
Remember that signet ring cells are cells
that have their nucleus pushed off
to one edge of the cell,
and the reason the nucleus is pushed off
is because the cell is full of mucus,
and the mucus displaces the nucleus.
Now that's the diffuse type of gastric cancer,
and that cancer can spread to both ovaries,
giving the patient something called
a Krukenberg tumor.
It is possible that mucinous carcinomas
from other sites could also spread to the ovary.
They would also be called Krukenberg tumor.
For example, the breast can develop a tumor
that can spread to the ovary,
in particular when the tumor in the breast
has signet ring cells,
for example, as would be seen
with lovular carcinoma.
Another example would be colon cancer,
which could be mucinous
and which could go and spread to both ovaries,
but the classic and the most common example
is the diffuse type of gastric carcinoma.
So that's a Krukenberg tumor.
Now, one important distinction to make,
and that is if you have mucinous tumors of the ovary,
you could ask the question,
is the mucinous tumor a primary tumor,
in which case it would, for example,
be a surface epithelial tumor that is mucinous?
Or is the tumor metastatic?
And one way by which we can make that distinction
is to look at whether the tumor involves both ovaries
or only involves one ovary.
If you have mucinous tumor involving only one ovary,
it's more likely to be
a primary surface epithelial mucinous tumor.
However, if the mucinous tumor involves both ovaries,
then it's more likely to have spread from a foreign site.
So that's the summary of the Krukenberg tumor,
and I've discussed the high yields in that summary.
The second type of metastatic involvement of the ovary
can be seen with pseudomyxoma peritoneiae.
Now, pseudomyxoma peritoneiae is a term that's used
to describe an abundant amount of mucin
present within the peritoneum.
Classically, it's also known as jelly belly
because you get all of this mucousy fluid
present within the abdomen.
Now, these patients who have pseudomyxoma peritoneiae,
the primary source, the key tumor that's causing that
is usually a tumor within the appendix.
And classically, it's a mucinous carcinoma of the appendix.
And often, that mucinous carcinoma of the appendix,
as it produces massive amounts of mucus
and creates the pseudomyxoma peritoneiae,
will have also metastasized to the ovary.
And so in this particular case,
the patients have a primary tumor of the appendix,
which then produces abundant mucin within the peritoneum
along with metastatic tumor to the ovaries.
So that's pseudomyxoma peritoneiae.
And that closes off our section on ovarian neoplasia.